Guide to the Adrien L. Hess Montana Science Fair Papers 1948-1967
Montana State University-Bozeman Library
Adrien L. Hess Montana Science Fair Papers
1948-1967
Montana State University-Bozeman Library, Merrill G Burlingame Special Collections P.O. Box 173320 Bozeman, MT 59717-3320 United States Phone (406) 994-4242 Fax (406) 994-2851 http://www.lib.montana.edu/archives/ University Archivist spcoll@www.lib.montana.edu
Collection 1195, MtBC, us
Hess, Adrien L.
.8 linear feet
The Adrien L. Hess papers dealing with the administration, preparation, and promotion of science fairs for Montana High school students contain letters, printed and mimeographed catalogs, newsletters, award winner lists, and other materials documenting fairs nationally as well as in Montana.
Biographical Note
Adrien Leroy Hess was born on January 18, 1908 in Johnson County, Missouri. He earned a bachelor of science degree in mathematics from Missouri Valley College in 1930, a bachelor’s degree in education from the Central Missouri State College in 1932, a master’s degree in Mathematics from the University of Montana in 1941, and a doctorate in mathematics from the University of Wisconsin in 1954. He taught math and coached high school at the Belfry and Fort Benton high schools prior to joining the mathematics department at Montana State College, Bozeman in 1945 and remained there until his retirement in 1972. He was an avid promoter of high school science students in Montana and founded the Montana Science Talent Search in 1947. Hess served as a judge in numerous district science fairs in Montana during his career and a scholarship was established in his name by the Montana Council of Teachers of Mathematics. Dr. Hess died in Bozeman on May 22, 1994.
The Adrien L. Hess papers dealing with the administration, preparation, and promotion of science fairs for Montana High school students contain letters, printed and mimeographed catalogs, newsletters, award winner lists, and other materials documenting fairs nationally as well as in Montana. The folders have been arbitrarily arranged based on location and chronology.
This collection is open for research.
Original letters, printed materials, exhibit calendars, and other materials created or collected by Adrien L. Hess pertaining to science fairs held at Montana high schools and colleges were donated to Montana State University by Hess in 1976. An additional folder of materials on the same topic also kept by Hess was transferred from the University Archives in the spring of 1983.
Children and Youth; Elementary and Secondary Education; Science; Montana
- "A History of District Science Fairs Held at Montana State College", "1956-1964" (Box-folder 1/1)
- First Montana State College district science fair, 1956 (Box-folder 1/2)
- Montana Science Fair. Miscellaneous Papers, Award winners, 1957; 1959; 1961-1964 (Box-folder 1/3)
- Montana State College, Bozeman. Catalog of exhibits; Scattered holdings of winners, 1957-1964; 1956-1964 (Box-folder 1/4)
  Catalog of exhibits: 1957-1964; Scattered holdings of winners: 1956-1964.
- Montana State University, Missoula. Catalog of exhibits, 1956-1064 (Box-folder 1/5)
  [missing 1963]
- Midland Empire Science Fair, Billings. Catalog of exhibits, 1958-1959 (Box-folder 1/6)
- Butte Regional Science Fair, Butte. Catalog of exhibits, 1956; 1958; 1962-1963; 1966 (Box-folder 1/7)
- Choteau High School. Echoes of Einstein Science Club, District Science Fair. Catalog of exhibits, 1957-1961 (Box-folder 1/8)
- Custer County High School. Science Fair. Catalog of exhibits, 1958-1960 (Box-folder 1/9)
- Great Falls Central - Ft. Benton High School. District 5 Science Fair. Catalog of exhibits, 1962-1964 (Box-folder 1/10)
- Helena Science Fair. Catalog of exhibits, 1959-1960 (Box-folder 1/11)
- Kalispell Northwest District Science Awards, 1958; 1960; 1961 (Box-folder 1/12)
- National Science Fair. Catalog of Exhibits. 1st-7th; 9-13, 1950-1956; 1958-1962 (Box-folder 1/13)
  Catalog of Exhibits. 1st-7th, 1950-1956, 9-13, 1958-1962.
- National Science Fair [Newsletter] 5th-11th, 15th, 1954-1960; 1964 (Box-folder 1/14)
- National Talent Science Searches, 1948-1954; 1956-1957; 1959-1960 (Box-folder 2/1)
- National Science Fair International, 8th-18th, 1957-1967 (Box-folder 2/2)
- Science Clubs of America. Information to inform leaders about how to start science projects. (Box-folder 2/3)
- Science Clubs of America. Affiliated Groups, 1959-1963 (Box-folder 2/4)
- Science Newsletter's with information about the National Talent Search, 1958-1967 (Box-folder 2/5)
- Montana State College District science fair, letters and reports, 1955-1965 (Box-folder 2/6)